<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A northern blast, or the spiritual Quaker converted: being soul-saving advice to the giddy people of England, who are running headlong to destruction. Wherein is shewed the manner of their meetings, in the county of Yorkshire, and Durham, their quakings, skreekings [sic] and ridiculous actions; also their fond and false restings of the scriptures. With a full examination, conviction of their tenets. / By G. Emmot, of Durham gent. formerly a brother amongst them, but now (by the help of God) converted, and established in the truth.</title>
            <author>Emmot, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84421</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866783</idno>
  <idno type="VID">168057</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501378</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E714A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E826_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207747</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866783</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866783e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E826[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A northern blast, or the spiritual Quaker converted: being soul-saving advice to the giddy people of England, who are running headlong to destruction. Wherein is shewed the manner of their meetings, in the county of Yorkshire, and Durham, their quakings, skreekings [sic] and ridiculous actions; also their fond and false restings of the scriptures. With a full examination, conviction of their tenets. / By G. Emmot, of Durham gent. formerly a brother amongst them, but now (by the help of God) converted, and established in the truth.</title>
                  <author>Emmot, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Lambert, Bookseller at the Ministers Gate in York,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Febr. 14 1654"; the final 5 in the imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>E714A is a copy of this which lacks prelims. If E714aA uses the same sheets as this, E714A matches that as well.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Quakers --  England --  Yorkshire --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168057:1"/>
            <p>A NORTHERN BLAST, OR THE SPIRITUAL QUAKER CONVERTED: Being Soul-saving Advice to the giddy people of <hi>England,</hi> who are running head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Destruction.</p>
            <p>Wherein are shewed the manner of their Meetings, in the County of <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> their Quakings, Skreekings and ridiculous Actions; Also their fond and false restings of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>WITH A full Examination, and Conviction of their Tenets.</p>
            <p>By G. EMMOT, of <hi>Durham</hi> Gent. formerly a Brother amongst them, but now (by the help of God) Converted, and Established in the Truth.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>R. Lambert,</hi> Bookseller at the Ministers Gate in <hi>York,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168057:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168057:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ʋch was the case of my speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Friend, having long time time wandered in the Meander of Religious Dubiousness, or rather blinde Zeale, as that (God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at length opened his Eyes, to behold the wonderfull things contained in his Law, Demonstrating by the Spirit the difference betwixt Truth and Falshood) he imparts to me (in private) this his long Circuition, or Shooting at Rovers, ere he could hit the Mark of a Faithfull and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Resolve. Who having related the several passages <hi>(Non audita sed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perta)</hi> I remembred that old Monastichon, <hi>Scire tuum nihil est, nisi te scire hoc sciat Alter.</hi> Wherefore deeming it illegall to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal
<pb facs="tcp:168057:3"/> whatsoever tends to Gods glory and his Churches good; what he promiscuously de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, I have onely endeavoured Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally to set in Order; presenting it to the publick view of each faithfull Christian, desirous to be informed, especially to thee who acceptest the willingnesse of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy well-wisher in Christ GEORGE EMMOT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168057:3"/>
            <head>THE SPIRITUAL QUAKER: OR Soulsaving Advice to the Brethren, held out by <hi>G. E.</hi> who formerly hath been sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but now (by the help of his God) is established in the Truth. These following lines were shewen me in a Vision in the Night, whereupon I arose and writ them into a Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Who is enspired, here may scan</l>
               <l>What I profess'd, what now I am.</l>
               <l>See thou abhor and fly the Ministers who Teach</l>
               <l>The quaking Saints; who cry Repentance ought to preach</l>
               <l>The naked truth; they speak Christs Sacred Gospel free;</l>
               <l>All other teaching's weak, Gods Messengers they bee.</l>
               <l>All private Conventicles embrace and hold them sweet,</l>
               <l>Avoid their Principles in Churches who do meet,</l>
               <l>Their Doctrine is but lyes, these are the Saints Divine.</l>
               <l>Their Visions Vanities, then chuse no way but mine.</l>
               <l>Who so in body quake, their Soul Salvation's seald,</l>
               <l>With Devils they partake, who unto Priests do yeild,</l>
               <l>Headlong to be cast down, whose Doctrine gives to thee</l>
               <l>The losse of Sions Crown, Heavens Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Psal.</hi> 8.8.</note> because thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto Babes.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have read of <hi>Ambrose</hi> Bishop of <hi>Millan,</hi> how he withstood the Emperour in his dayes, at the entrance of the Church, because he thought him altogether unfit to be partaker of such holy things: and we all know, how zealous <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:168057:4"/> was in his way (though erroneous) persecuting the Saints. And I my selfe confesse (though not at the Door, or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Church, or Publick place of meeting with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood) have used all my Art to disswade from entring, as altogether unfit, in respect they were (as I supposed) a rabble of iniquous persons, not worthy the Saints to interveen, and though with <hi>Paul</hi> I did not (because I wanted power) persecute, yet I undermined, and by private means plotted all I could, which might tend to their ruine.</p>
            <p>But when that Gospel Love (which thorow a selfe end displaced) was placed againe in me, I began to wonder at my selfe, and wandering Oppositions, in thwarting and overthwarting the Gospels precepts, believing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (though nere so true) but what mine own private spirit (though nere so false) did move me to; as though I had in a moment gained more then <hi>Paul,</hi> who was wrapt into the third Heaven, or superlative favour of his Christ; many were the raptures which I dreamed to have, but all was but a Fancy or Somnaical, when I came to Descend, which must be by Humility ere we can Ascend to Eternity; I viewed (by the assistance of the Spirit) a number of misled soules, walking in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of selfe Man, even the whole frame out of course, which caused my passionate soule to burst forth into these words: <hi>Arise, O God, judge the Earth, fill their Faces with shame, that they may seek thy name O Lord, who say, Let us take to our selves the houses of God in possession; that all may know, that thou whose Name alone is Jehovah, art the most high over all the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My proud and lofty thoughts, being thus (by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Love) brought down, I now wish also, that all who have been (in the like nature) seduced, may humble themselves under the mighty hand of God, and (if they please) read what here the spirit of God hath given me to speak.</p>
            <p>I am not able with the Rhetorician to adorn my work with some faire flowers, or graceful words, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168057:4"/> might adde a lustre to the subsequence, or place some large Encomium to stand in stead of a seemly Portal to the Fabrick; but my desire is to rear no golden Image, but a poor, humble, plain, rough-hewn work (held out from that Text of <hi>Jeremy</hi>) composed in Love.</p>
            <div type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>LAMENT. 3.40.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let us search and try our works, and turn again to the Lord.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head type="sub">First Search.</head>
               <p>IN this part of the Exhortation I have been industrious, seeking how I might (by any meanes) grapple with my Christ; and leaving the worldly things, I betook my selfe to seek amongst the Papists; whose Gntleman-Usher was Antiquity (as they told me.) These (I found) would have a Name in the world, to be called the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, implying others to be Catholicks too; but when Divines told me that the signification of the word was Universal (denoting the universality of Christs flock, having in all parts of the world some who have not bent their knee to <hi>Baal</hi>) I left that Name, and sought into their Service and Divotion, where I found blinde <hi>Bartimeus</hi> more zealous then the quick eyed <hi>Linceus; Croesus</hi> dumb son more troubled to perform his actions, then the nimblest tongu'd Orator; I mean those who were blind by ignorance, and so dumb as that they scarce could speak one of the Scriptures sentences: yet were these busied to rumble and run over their Beadiols, though in the interim they would be pleased sometimes to discourse upon worldly matters, and fall to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion again: These poor soules have their Lay Books, but they must not have the Bible Book; for why? it is a Mystery. I went and sought further, where in an inner
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168057:5"/> roome <hi>I</hi> came to Masse (as they call'd it) where was an Altar richly deckt, furnished as though a banquet for a King were there prepared, the Crucifix, the Tapers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Frankincense, the Sacring Bell; all these though bookes to some, read small sense to my Intellect. The Crucifix tis true might stand without a doulian adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from my body, the Light was also good, especially within a darksome room, and the smell of Incense, where noysome savours and infections were suspected; but for my darkened soule small light <hi>I</hi> found, which would not (by a waxen Taper, or wooden Statue) be led, but by an inward light, proceeding from the Spirit, and Christ the onely Crucifix. Then <hi>I</hi> lent my Ear with attentivenesse unto the Teacher, who was very costly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed with Cope and Vestment, and many other feat Crepundians; <hi>I</hi> heard his first beginning, which being in the Latine tongue, <hi>I</hi> stood as dumb, or if been deafe, it had not mattered concerning what was spoken, so that my sense had not been weakned for the future. True it is, <hi>I</hi> could from those Grammatical rudiments, which formerly <hi>I</hi> understood, snatch like a hungry beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger one bone from him, which was, <hi>Introibo ad Altare Dei:</hi> these though his first words, served me chewing till the last, how to construe them: what more he spake was unto me a Riddle; his cringing Congies, lifting up a boxe on high, salutes, kisses, was but as a Mask to my masked understanding. Then I remembred that when the Apostle taught at the Feast of Pentecost, every one heard (who was there) in their own language, the Rites of Christ; which place of Scripture (having well consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) brought me back from <hi>Romes</hi> fair shew, to see what the Reformation promised.</p>
               <p>Into a Cathedral <hi>I</hi> came, where was the Table deckt, but yet no Crucifix, the Service in the vulgar tongue <hi>I</hi> heard, the Organs also in the Quire was pleasure to my sense, and rather because reading Doctor <hi>Butlers</hi> Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to Musick, <hi>I</hi> had gained some small knowledge therein, whereupon (this being known) a dimminitive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168057:5"/> Priest brought me a Book, which part suting my voice, <hi>I</hi> joyned with heart, and voice, and understanding also. Here some time <hi>I</hi> stayed till fear possessed me with some intended alteration.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>I</hi> liked the Minister as well without as with his Surplice on; it was the Word <hi>I</hi> thirsted after; not the white appearance of his Lawn-like sleeves, but the white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and purity of Doctrine, which having heard, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and being verst in all the principles, I left the Railes and heard one teach, who had brought them from the Table to the Pulpit: this was an <hi>Odium</hi> unto me. After this <hi>I</hi> was invited to one, who as he has told me preached Christ, he (I do confesse having been his Auditor) not onely preached Christ by his Doctrine, as he seemed, but each tenth part (if not more) of his Sermon was Christ; her was much talking of Christ.</p>
               <p>Then my brethren Professors told me of many new lights, which the Spirit had demonstrated, amongst which the Independents was the onely light; <hi>I</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to remove from darknesse sought this light, where <hi>I</hi> beheld some praying one while, and some another, all being tolerated (who had a gift) to exercise: my selfe was there invited, yet <hi>I</hi> durst not take too much upon me. Newes was also brought of a Northern Candle, or Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Comet which cast such illustrious beams, as was not formerly seen or heard, the Woman Teacher called <hi>Barbara,</hi> to whom among the rest <hi>I</hi> went on Pilgrimage; she having opened her mouth, spake (as then <hi>I</hi> thought) like to a Saint in Christ, and Divinely taught; but that which was a stumbling block to me, was that place of Scripture in the first Epistle of <hi>Timothy,</hi> the second Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the twelfth verse; where <hi>Paul</hi> having as it should seem espied the arrogancy of some such like effeminate Doctors, would not suffer them.</p>
               <p>Neverthelesse, I still seeking, met (at the length) one of my old acquaintance, who took upon him to perswade me, that <hi>I</hi> was but in the Letter still, and unlesse I went a degree higher, there was small hope to be saved, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168057:6"/> terrifying drug wrought so strongly, as that I gave ear to what was spoken; he seemed to read a Lesson from the Spirit, wished me to look within, and think of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teaching, which I knew before was the Sermons ending, and the hearers beginning; he thought he taught me, yet affirmed all teaching was in vain, and gave me Scripture for it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. Hence I quite relinquished what I heretofore professed; the Church was but a Steeple house, and whatsoever appartained ridiculous; the Bible I threw it by, esteeming nothing of it but a dead Letter, though what I spoke was still from what <hi>I</hi> had heard taught and learned from thence, which I (being ignorantly blinded) could not then conceive.</p>
               <p>Thus being new Moulded, <hi>I</hi> met my friend <hi>George Fox,</hi> whom I heard Syllabically dictate, as though he could not utter, but what the Spirit forced forth, busied like a Woman in travel to bring forth, though an abortive: he let me see what <hi>I</hi> was before (as he said) wading in a Whirlepoole, who with one finger helped me out, and set me on dry ground, confirming <hi>I</hi> had Christ now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me. After comes she that did the bottle bring, who purged me of all dregs and made me perfect, for by once tasting <hi>I</hi> was so transformed, as that to tell, <hi>I</hi> know not how to tell, but light <hi>I</hi> was though not in light: the world was now an Idol, my cloath and new apparrel, with ribbands, points, and such like furniture, seemed like so many Hags or furies sent from Hell to torture me, whereupon like a man distracted, <hi>I</hi> rent them off as obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious, and threw them by as pernicious, put on an old cast suit of apparrel, a small coard about my Hat, to have in readinesse for that which without Gods special Providence <hi>I</hi> was running to. In this same garb <hi>I</hi> thought my selfe not worldly, but all spiritual: my calling now <hi>I</hi> slighted, would not be careful for any Family, (like an Infidel or worse) but unto travel would betake my self, amongst my quaking companions, amongst their <hi>Settering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonians, Maltoneers, Paludarians I</hi> was, and there embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my brother <hi>Collins,</hi> who had a spiritual Revelation,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168057:6"/> (as he reported) to stand naked on Kerby-Moor side Market Crosse (not nailed on the Crosse) and speake the naked truth, where I expected the comming of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertonians, supposing to have accompanied them to mount <hi>Sion,</hi> ere the day of Doom (as 'tis called) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, which <hi>Ratcliffes</hi> wife the Prophetesse held out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us to be within a small number of dayes, but some of those Maltoneers who kept Holliday enterrupted our passage, and told the vision was but false, they had a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of delusion, which I suppose was all one as if he had said, the Saints have now the Divel in them.</p>
               <p>Now having thus far fought, I desire that in the next place we may try our wayes according to the Apostles Counsel, <hi>Try the Spirits whether they be of God or no;</hi> and what better rule can there be, or square to frame our worke by, that so it may be fitly compact and joyne together, then that Evangelical Touchstone the Gospel, which is the true distinguisher of all false met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, or chiefe demonstrator of all false Prophets; and though we had one (not inferiour unto <hi>Paul</hi>) teaching amongst us, yet would I follow the example of the Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: try that place, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. they tryed by the rule of Scripture whether he was fit to be credited yea or no, and in the first place I desire a little to try the Papists, who officiating in an unknown tongue contradict the expresse words of their own Bible; try 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.1. to 16. They would administer the Communion, but not in both kinds to the Laity, contrary to the expresse words of their own Bible; try <hi>Io.</hi> 6.35. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. They will not allow the vulgarity to read the Scriptures, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse words of their own Bible, <hi>Io.</hi> 5.39. and try 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. They affirme ignorance to be the mother of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrary to the words of their own Bible, <hi>Io.</hi> 17.3. &amp; againe <hi>Psal.</hi> 143.8, 9, 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.38. They bid us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship Saints and Angels, contrary to the words of their Bible, <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.16. and try <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18, to 23. Let us try our ways. Now if you object against me why I stand to try the Papists as not appertaining, I will (though not here) shew my reason, when <hi>I</hi> have tryed our selves.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168057:7"/>
               <p>First then to try our wayes, we flye from the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or publick meeting to the Church on the Lords day, as scorning to enter such prophane Steeple-houses, or accompany amongst such known sinners, saying as those people did of old; try <hi>Esa.</hi> 65.5. contrary to Christs example, who (though he was all purity, in whom was no spot at all, the spiritual giver and teacher, or giver of the Spirit) entred into the Synagogue upon the Sabbath day; try <hi>Io.</hi> 18.20. and <hi>Paul</hi> also the spiritual Quaker, try <hi>Acts</hi> 9.20. We avoid the general assemblies, because they are sinners, contrary to Christs example who accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied amongst Prodigals and Harlots: try <hi>Io.</hi> 15.1, 2. And contrary also to the expresse words of the Bible, try <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22, to 25. And doth not the Spirit in another place hold out unto us, that the godly and the wicked cannot (neither ought) to be separated until he send his reapers (the blessed Angels) who shal divide the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? try <hi>Mat.</hi> 13 24, &amp; 29, 39. <hi>verses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> We say the place is nothing but a heap of stones, compacted and joyned together, and wheresoever two or three or more of the Saints are gathered together, there is the Church.</p>
               <p>To this (according as Divines doe teach, and we must also confesse) I answer, the word hath a two-fold sense; sometimes taken for the publick place of meeting which is the literal signification, but spiritually for the body whereof Christ Jesus is the head; and true it is, the place without the Saints is but an edifice or structive made with hands, and still no more; yet when in that place they are convened, it must needs be confest to be a more holy place then any of our own houses thatch't over with Hypocrisie, and though they want Steeples, yet have they Steeple-height Iniquity; <hi>Vide</hi> the Commission of several transgressions which I need not name, but rather say with <hi>Paul;</hi> try <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.12. Now whether of these are more fit for the publick meeting of the Saints, try <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.17. And are not the Saints the Temple of the Holy Ghost, whereby each creature is sanctified by prayer,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168057:7"/> and giving of thanks, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. Let us try our wayes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Ministers or Teachers of the Word: these are a stumbling block or stone of offence in our way, at which and where we usually throw our fire-balls; first we say there needs no teaching (notwithstanding we our selves would teach) consrary to the expresse words of the Bible; try <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15. &amp; try 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. to the end of the Chapter, and <hi>Paul</hi> was called the Teacher of the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>That which we commonly are adversant at, is their life and conversation. In this let me not be partial, but conscientious to all; for if it were not (<hi>I</hi> confesse) more the special mercy of Christ, or rather a miraculous work of grace, many of them would rather eradicate then build the Fabrick; some like the Whale Fish devouring the rest of their followers, predominating (I meane) or proudly lording over them, contrary to the words of the Bible; try 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. Others I have known though meerly sottish and compatricial, by some favour, obtaine a living or benefit of a large size, though the Parishioner for the benefit of their souls are glad to pay Excise; some are covetous, lascivious, proud, envious; not that I accuse any, but rather excuse, because I know love covereth a multitude of sins: others, so poor their words are not of force, especially amongst those who desire the Priest should beare rule by his meanes. But now let us try our wayes. I must not deny Christ because <hi>Pete, r</hi> did betray the truth, because <hi>Iudas</hi> did, or forsake the Gospel because I spy some <hi>Simon Magus</hi> or a Simonist amongst the Apostles, but rather try where <hi>I</hi> finde a faithful Teacher; and if the place of thy abode in this prove deficient, wanting a painful man, then try thy self, thou art in part the cause; try <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15. God viewed in this Prophets dayes how both Priests and people were profane; try <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.9, to 17. which place I have alledged my self against the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters; but now try the Ministers who Preach Christ in his Word, doe they not speak the truth? the Priests before mentioned, taught lyes, suborned evil doers, held out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168057:8"/> visions of their own heart, whom (if any such now thou truely find) <hi>I</hi> wish avoid, yet pray for them, not revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Teachers, because tis contrary to the words of the Bible, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. for the Prophet saith, <hi>They are the Messengers of the Lord of Hosts,</hi> and tis they by whom God is pleased to speak in publique to his people, whose lips shal preserve knowledge, <hi>but because they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned the holy Covenant of Levi, therefore are they become contemptible amongst the people;</hi> try <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.2, to 10. The Gospel stiles them Ambassadors, as bringing the message of some mighty Prince; try 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20, but we usually (as in other matters) in this turned; Questionists, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding who they were for say we, the Apostles went from one place to another teaching, not seeking after some great Personage or Living ere they would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to preach Christ.</p>
               <p>In this we misconstrue the different Case and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apostles then, and the Ministers who are now; In them was a Law of necessity, both from Christs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as also their condition; for whoso intentively goes into an uncouth Island to convert, must not (neither can) at the first, seek to get to an establisht meanes, because he must not be resident in any one place, which was the Apostles case, yet had they what their brethren had, and were commanders of it; try <hi>Act.</hi> 4.34, 35. &amp;c. and again <hi>Act</hi> 5.1, 2. they having made known and manifested the power of Christ in each part of their circuits, would not therefore leave them before they had ordained Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers fit for that calling in their absence; try <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. <hi>Lets try our wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> These Ministers teach for hire, and therefore are but hirelings.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>I</hi> answer, if thou and <hi>I</hi> would but perform the same unto them, that the followers of the Apostles did, this Bramble-bush would be converted into a Lilly; but <hi>I</hi> fear <hi>Briarius</hi> disease is too frequent amongst the caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized professors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> do remember the Apostle speakes of false Prophets,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168057:8"/> who in the <hi>last daies</hi> shall make merchandise of Soules, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 3. such are these <hi>I</hi> deem who ere they hazard the loosing of their worldly benefit they will agree to the Protestation, subscribe the Scotch Covenant, and be a Witnesse to the Engagement if the Papist should predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate; tis likely they would go to the Masse-Schoole, if they might be admitted, and learn how to say a Masse. But what makes this against the lawful competency or subsistency of a painful Teacher? try <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.4. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. though <hi>Paul</hi> used not that which he pleads law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful (meaning a sufficient meanes or maintenance) yet he would exhort the people to Contributions and Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; try <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.26, 27. and shall we say that <hi>Paul</hi> was not partaker of what he gathered? Now to certifie who these Teachers are, whom we say to be sent, consider who they were that <hi>Pauls</hi> Ordination made Elders, who after prayer and fasting of the Church, were commended unto the Lord, to be as it seemes Teachers of the Gospel. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. and those seven <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5, 6. and ere <hi>Paul</hi> was sent upon any Message to preach for the conversion of Soules, he received the Ordination of the Church: try <hi>Acts</hi> 13.3. and this gife he warnes his Disciple <hi>Timothy</hi> not to neglect: try 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 4.14. Now try thou that takest upon thee to be a Publick Teacher, hast thou received a <hi>Paul</hi>-like Vision? or if so, hast thou received the laying on of the hands of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry? if not, beware thou take not too much upon thee: for though the Act may seem good, and thy inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as meaning right, yet if this proceed frome one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, not for that service ordained, tis petty Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son against the <hi>King of Kings, Lord of Lords, the onely Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Princes;</hi> try 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Lets try, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly the Magistrates are no Magistrates unto us: wee'l bow the knee to none, neither call any Father; for one is our Father which is in Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23, 9. not knowing that the Scripture there speaks of the <hi>eternal</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to the saying, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2 10, and moreover it was their custome (as appears from our Saviours
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168057:9"/> words) to call <hi>Abraham</hi> their Father; try <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.39. which Christ strives to take away, teaching them that God is their Father, in respect of Creation, Redemption, &amp;c. But now try, shall we not use the word Father to any, or any such like phrase of Reverence to persons of Dignity? try 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.15. And <hi>Daniel</hi> vouchsafes to call <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> Lord and King, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.19. try <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Paul</hi> saith likewise he was a father to the people, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. and so the Magistrates are, or at leastwise should be as Nursing Fathers, and nursing Mothers, <hi>Esa.</hi> 49.22. and as touching that honour due unto the Teachers, try 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. to 17. Thus though the <hi>Morian</hi> statutes we abhor, yet <hi>Chatadalian</hi> Principles are by us <hi>retained:</hi> we would have a Purity, which (who knowes not?) would at length prove Disparity: ye take too much upon you, was the cry in <hi>Moses</hi> time, but they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed in Gods good time: then try 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the word we terme a dead Letter, not knowing that even our bodies and soules (though living on this Earth) without Christ, and his quickening grace are dead: try <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. So the Word, as 'tis a Letter writ with Pen and Ink into a Book, is not that Life, but the quickening Spirit which faith believes to go a long with it. But try, if it be not with thee as the Apstoles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied it should be in the <hi>last daies,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. For where shall we have that quickening power of Conversion, if not in the Word? try <hi>Rom.</hi> 25.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.21. The Devil tempting Christ (who was the Essential word) encounters him with an old Text of the written, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative word; and Christs answer is retortively the same: try <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6. which places (alledged by Christ) did so maule the Devils impudency, as that he leaves the Son of God, without taking further leave to dispute the matter.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the people who are not of the same opinion with us, we look squintly upon them, with a scornfull reproach, or passing in haste a rash sentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168057:9"/> as if we had viewed the secret will of Gods Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or seen the private roll of Predestination, contrary to the words of the Bible: try <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1, to 5. We blame them also for their apparrel, which (I confesse) may be, and is in many beyond their calling, yet is not this the Pride the spirit speaks of, nor that which we our selves so much professe spiritual teaching, for in the heart this serpent lies; Neither do we read that <hi>Solomon</hi> who was (according to his degree) very sumptuous &amp; costly in his Robes, Plate, Hangings, Attendants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was blamed for these, but for his several women, who caused him to neglect and chuse an unknown God. Not that I (mistake me not) allow any more, (then ever) of gaudy and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate habit, but wish that all may be performed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as is expressed in the words of the Bible: try 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Lets try our wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis now time I give Response to what was promised, to wit, why I medled with the Papists: and my Reason is, to try our wayes, how neer we run into their Abscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, if not Absurdities: They term those on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Hereticks: We term them vile who are against us. They would have the Bible put into the Popes Pokeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for the Ministers of the Gospel to be sent into some barbarous Island, to seeke out a new Plantation, or to live like the Prophet upon the bread of Adversity, and water of Affliction; and whatsoever belongs to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, they hold erroneous, not onely speaking against them, but endeavouring by their several Plots and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Machinations, for their, and all the Gospels ruine: And are we not posting on the same road, without a guide to Tyburne? <hi>Lets try our wayes.</hi> Is not this a means to make more Papists, or turn to Atheists? <hi>Lets, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, lets try and seek the Radix of our preposterous wayes, which like a strong gust of wind, violently turnes about the Windmill of our affections. And if here you demand what are our setled Tenets, I could never yet find any so strongly setled as to resolve me: each Vulture-like,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168057:10"/> gnawing upon the invented prey of his own brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick Fancy, whirlling about, being dislocated from the Centre.</p>
               <p>Neverthelesse, the first Radix (as Inference hath taught taught me) of these distempers, I find to be ignorance, misconstruing the Scriptures sence, for want of such a <hi>Philip</hi> as the Eunuch had to expound it clearly. He read the Bible, but knew not what it meant, yet was he not so bolp as I have been to frame an Exposition from his own private spirit, try <hi>Acts</hi> 8.30, 31. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Lets try, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this condition of ignorance, <hi>I</hi> read that place of <hi>Esa.</hi> 20. where God commands the people to go naked, speaking or demonstrating the shameful Captivity of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> which place <hi>I</hi> thought sufficient for any to go naked: <hi>I</hi> also took that Text into considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slon, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.18. as though here <hi>I</hi> had enough to prove our quaking. Not knowing that the former was an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary voice of prefiguration, and this other deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the broken and Contrite heart, spoke of by <hi>David:</hi> for so Divines hold out from the Original, which signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a kind of sorrrowful apprehension of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments approaching. <hi>Lets try, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, another Radix, as my Ezperience holds out, is a sinister end. Concerning which, let each one search and tty their own hearts, and there it may be, they will finde (though not confesse) the same conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>I</hi> gave my Vote to <hi>Lilburnes</hi> late Demonstration for removing that <hi>Iewish</hi> Idol of Tyth-taking, incited espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from an inward principle of hoping to gaine that part which my selfe was accustomed to pay. This Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (<hi>I</hi> fear) makes the Commons cry with wider mouths a <hi>H.</hi> then ever the Western men did cry a <hi>Savile. Lets try our wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Radix (as my experience still speakes) is pride, though <hi>I</hi> could not then discern it: for I thought my selfe no whit inferiour to the greatest person, because the Text saith, God is no respecter of persons. When
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168057:10"/> I could give the Language (thou) to any (though nere so eminent) <hi>I</hi> supposed my self now grown wise (though my folly never more appeard) and Leper-like could keep my Hat unvailed as though my <hi>Pericranium</hi> stood need of scalping, or that I feared another should (by pulling it off) espie more hair then wit.</p>
               <p>The fourth Radix (as my Experience still teacheth) is a wilfulnesse rather then a religious willingnesse; for <hi>I</hi> would then hear no Bible proofe, that spoke against my way, framing some s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nge Exposition (contrary to all Comentators) upon it, like unto those people of which <hi>David</hi> speaks; try <hi>Psal.</hi> 82.5. Whatsoever proceeded from the voice of a Minister (my affection being averse) was but as sounding Brasse, or the tinckling of a Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal; was not this the reason why Christ left off his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles amongst his Natives? try <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.58. In this condition <hi>I</hi> had forgot, that learning made me know how to read the Bible, and so to hear of God, and all his Attributes; for if <hi>I</hi> had never known the Bible, neither read nor heard, my condition (<hi>I</hi> suppose) would have been otherwise. Not that the reading, or searching of the Bibles precepts, causeth evil, but tis the powerful o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of Gods spirit, who when he seeth man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man slight the Truth, takes away his Candle of illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and fire of Love; and some grow both blinde and envious; then try that place <hi>Io.</hi> 5.46.47. <hi>Lets try our wayes:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now follows the other part of the Exhortation, which is, <hi>Turne againe unto the Lrrd;</hi> but in this case twas with me (as may be with thee who readest) <hi>I</hi> would not heare that voice of the Charmer, charmed he never so wisely, till at length a strange kind of inward Susurration from whence <hi>I</hi> know not, seeing the wind blowes where it listeth, seized upon my Soule; whereupon my wilfull violency (on a suddaine) was changed to <hi>Suaveolency,</hi> and that word which ere while <hi>I</hi> valued not, begun to be of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimation. I was after this invited by my singular good friend <hi>Gnothiticon</hi> to discourse a little with a Minister,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168057:11"/> who formerly (as now) loved me dearly, by whose per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion at length (though sore bickering I had within my selfe, which strove to pull me back, dilating the shame which would follow, by relinquishing what I had undertaken, and so strongly maintained) I steerd my course towards that place, where being arived, he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, as the Child of God (borne of the Almighty, whh is Love) begun to hold out the Scriptures sence (in and upon sundry places) unto one, whereat I former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly stumbled, laying open the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>itual application (or that mystery of Godlinesse) which I so much thirsted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not destroying the Letter, which was my fault for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly: he explained unto me whole Man, consisting of a Natural and a Spiritual part, the one rebelling against the other, yet cannot be utterly disjoyned until the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time (which <hi>Job</hi> so strongly waited for) become to a period, which Spirit or Spiritual treasures we have (saith <hi>Paul</hi>) in earthen vessels: but when these Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles shall be dissolved, we have a house (we know by the) Spirit) not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. He also declared the manifold infirmities sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Gods people, which might cause <hi>Paul</hi> to chasten his Body with fasting, least when he had taught to others, he himselfe should be a Reprobate. After this he wished me to consider that place of Scripture, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. Where having taken the Bible he descanted of the new Creature, or Creature made new by conversion, into which a gap being (by the power of the Spirit) made, the waters from the Fountain of living waters, do plenteously flow: at the first like the waters of <hi>Mara</hi> seems bitter; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while prove dulcide, sweeter then honey or the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney comb. From the sixth Text he hath shewed how those that are taught in the word, should communicate to those that teach in all good things. From whence he drew a conclusion concerning the necessity of the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one man another; for Eternity (saith he) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man could not understand his Characters, sends his son <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> not as a God, or Spirit speaking unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168057:11"/> man, but in the form of man, and very man, that he might speak, and man might understand the duty of man.</p>
               <p>He also framed some Morals (according to Christs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) for convincing of mine error, and confirming the Truth, amongst which he held out this following Parable for one; <hi>Suppose</hi> (saith he) <hi>thou wenst to pass into some forraign Island, where comming to the Haven to take Ship, thou art entertained into a fair new Vessel, newly lanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, having a skilful Pilot, strong Masts, new Saile-cloaths, well rig'd, and well furnished with all tacklings, fit to ride the Maine, and at length the Wind blowes faire, the Pilot calls, but thou and the rest of the Passengers, because you have had your abode some small time at the waters side, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to know the Time and Tide as well as he, and therefore you reply to his call, with an answer, Let him be calling, we are wise enough. On a suddain the wind grows rough, the billows beat, and the stormes tempestuous, then no passage at all; is it not just that such should lose their voyage?</hi> Prov. 1.24. Another he took from the Bible, where he divinely held out, how that Christ stood continually knocking with a hammer upon the Anvile or heart of man; try <hi>Can.</hi> 5.2. and this Hammer he also shewed me to be the Word of God, try <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. in which Chapter from the subse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent verses, he explained the false Hammers which they use; who take upon them to prophecy false dreams, and cause the people to erre, vers. 32.</p>
               <p>My intent is not to take upon me the part of a <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logian,</hi> for which office I am altogether unable, saying, who is fit for these things? but those whom God hath set apart, to apply their studious endeavours to search for the golden Minerals, or mysteries of godlinesse, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto them from the spirit of God by prayer and supplication. These I know would spin out the words into several threads, which might be wond up upon the Wheele of mans Intellect, first denoting from the word <hi>Turn,</hi> a kind of standing still, from pursuing the purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed intentions. Secondly, <hi>Turn again,</hi> which implies a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168057:12"/> Reversion or going back to seek something which was lost. Thirdly, <hi>Turne againe to the Lord,</hi> points out the But or Mark, at which all the Arrows of our Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Thoughts, Words, and Actions should be shot.</p>
               <p>But this Motion is beyond my sphere, I onely desire in brotherly love, that thou (whosoever hast been se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced) wouldst fly to the Lord with <hi>Davids</hi> words; try <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.33. I have (by the assistance of Gods spirit) chosen the way of truth, and laid Gods judgements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, which way I wish to all. <hi>I cryed unto the Lord</hi> (saies <hi>David) in my troubles, and he delivered me out of my distresse:</hi> if thou wilt but turne by praying, God will turn to thee by promising, and performing what he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. This heavenly duty was so prevalent, that we read it entered into the eares of Eternity from <hi>Cornelius,</hi> before he knew Christ; try <hi>Acts</hi> 10.4. &amp; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14, 15. And my counsel is also that thou turne with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable respect upon the painful Minister, who watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for thy soule, and can according to the saying of the Poet,
<q>
                     <l>Observe, Confirme, Apply, make use,</l>
                     <l>Whose Life strives to Reform abuse.</l>
                  </q> And pray also with <hi>David,</hi> that thy heart may be sound in Christs precepts, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.80. True it is, <hi>Ahab</hi> would call for Prophets, but they (we all know) were idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, but <hi>Jehosaphat</hi> enquires for one of the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> also having received the rayling Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Rabshekah,</hi> takes not upon himselfe, but sends for the Prophet to pray; try 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.1.4. Others without doubt he might have chosen, but he admits of none (but who was for that office) to speak in publick. <hi>David</hi> also enters into his closet, which he also holds out to others; and tis Christs counsel, see <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. For what thou hast heard in publique, shall not (it may be) inwardly be revealed unto thy soul, till thou enterest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168057:12"/> thy private Chamber, where then thou shalt plainly see within the closet of thy heart, and shalt with <hi>John</hi> the Divine behold the City of God, the new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> the spiritual <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Attendants, the Gates, the keepers of those Gates, with the keyes thereof, all held out from <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. Let the word of God a be Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn to thy seet, and a light unto thy paths, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.105. &amp; <hi>Psal.</hi> 119 9. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.31. But least <hi>I</hi> seem too Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix, <hi>I</hi> will shut up my desires with the Prophets words, <hi>Isa.</hi> 30.20. hoping that <hi>Though the Lord give us the bread of adversity, and the waters of affliction, yet shall not our Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers be removed into a corner any more, but our eyes shall see our Teachers, and our ears shall bear that voice saying, This is the way; And as many as walke according to this Rule, peace be on them and mercy, and upon the Israel of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Search, Try, and Turn unto the Lord who gave</l>
                  <l>Thy Soul to thee, and also must it save.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>